Register of the Robert Holtzmann Papers, 1912-1943
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert Holtzmann Papers,
1912-1943
49015
Holtzmann, Robert, 1883-
8 manuscript boxes, 3 microfilm reels, 4 envelopes (4.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, pamphlets, leaflets, newspaper issues, clippings, and photographs, relating primarily to the activities of the Tannenbergbund, a right-wing German political organization, active from 1926 to 1933, founded by General Erich Ludendorff. Includes correspondence with E. Ludendorff.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1949.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Ludendorff, Erich, 1865-1937.; Tannenbergbund.; Nationalism--Germany.; Germany.; Germany--History--1918-1933.; Germany--Politics and government--1918-1933.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, writings, pamphlets, leaflets, newspaper issues, clippings, and photographs, relating primarily to the activities of the Tannenbergbund, a right-wing German political organization, active from 1926 to 1933, founded by General Erich Ludendorff. Includes correspondence with E. Ludendorff.
Biographical Note
1883 Born in Duerrheim/Baden
1904 Became a lieutenant in the Imperial German Army. Later transferred to the Infantry Regiment Grossherzog v. Baden Nr-126 in Strassburg
1913 Promoted to First-Lieutenant, Imperial German Army
1916 From November until the end of the war was commander of Flying Division I on the Western Front, and of Flying Division 16 in the East and in Serbia
1920 In January resigned his commission in the armed service. In the same month took a position with the firm Starck-Michael & Co., Berlin, as a commercial employee responsible for the purchasing of coal tar and tar products
1922 In January took a position with the firm Herrmann C. Starck, a stock brockerage in Berlin
1963 Died
Container List
- Correspondence of Robert Holtzmann, 1920-1941 (Box 1-2)
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Includes letters sent to and received from General Erich Ludendorff.
  - Adermann, 1932 (First name unknown) (Box 1)
  - Aero Club von Deutschland, 1924
  - Ahlemann, Georg, 1926-1927, 1929
  - Alsleben, Kurt, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Altmann, Martin, 1932
  - Aplos, 1932 (First name unknown)
  - Arnswalder, Landrat der, 1933 (District Magistrate of Arnswalde)
  - Arnim, V., Co., 1925
  - Bahr, Max, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Basler Nachrichten, 1933
  - Beer, 1935 (First name unknown)
  - Bennewitz, Georg, 1930
  - Berlin
    - Heer Generalstaatsanwalt beim Landgericht, 1937
    - Kriegervereinhaus, 1928
    - Der Polizeipraesident, 1932
    - Tannerbergbund e.d., Landesleitung Gross-Berlin, 1927
  - Berliner Staedtische Elektrizitaetswerke A.G.-Rechnungsbueuro, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Biermann, Wilhelm, 1929, 1930, 1932
  - Blomberg, General Werner von, 1935, 1936
  - Blockelberg, von, 1932 (First name unknown)
  - Bonin, Doktor von, 1930 (First name unknown)
  - Borman, Martin, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Bueba, 1925 (First name unknown)
  - Buecheler, Anton, 1922
  - Buehler, Wilhelm, 1936
  - Burr, Hermann, 1933-1934
  - Cecile von Mecklenburg-Schwerin, Frau Kronprizessin des Deutschen Reiches und Preussen, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Chef des Generalstabes des Heeres, 1936
  - Demmin, Landrat des Kreises, 1933
  - Deutsche Tageszeitung, 1924
  - Deutscher Treubund, 1921
  - Deutschvoelkische Freiheitspartei, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Diels, Geheime Staatspolizei Z.H. des Herrn Ober-Regierungsrat, 1933
  - Drawerk, Alexander, Dr., 1925
  - Eberstein, Freiherr Karl von, 1925
  - Elsner, 1928 (First name unknown)
  - Falk, Wilhelm, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Finking, Ernst, 1926
  - Foertsch, Hermann, 1935
  - Frank, Herbert, 1934
  - Frankfurt Regierungs - Praesident, 1933
  - Frink, Dr., 1925, 1933 (First name unknown) (Box 1)
  - Fritsch, Freiherr, Werner von, 1932, 1934
  - Fritzsche, Georg, 1930-1933
  - Fuegner, Kurt, 1936
  - Fuerstlich - Hohenzollenschen Domaene und Forstverwaltung Sigmaringen, Der Praesident, 1933
  - Gansser, Emil, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Geck, 1926 (First name unknown)
  - Geserick, Paul, 1923-1924
  - Geyer, Kurt, 1926
  - Gieren, G., 1925
  - Goebbels, Dr. Joseph, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Goehring, 1933 (First name unknown)
  - Goering, Hermann, 1933
  - Goldbeck-Lowe, 1925 (German Consul in Helsinki)
  - Golz, Karl, 1932
  - Goltz, 1932 (First name unknown) (Box 1)
  - Gossrau, 1936 (First name unknown)
  - Graff, Georg, 1924, 1926
  - Greifenberg/Pommern, 1932, 1933
  - Guertner, Franz, 1936
  - Hass, A., 1926 (Box 1)
  - Handtmann, 1933 (First name unknown)
  - Harms, 1925 (First name unknown)
  - Hausmann, Arno, 1925
  - Heltge, Dr., 1932, 1933 (First name unknown)
  - Hemper, 1931 (First name unknown) (Box 1)
  - Hess, Alizabeth, 1933
  - Hess, Rudolf, 1935
  - Heun, C., 1929 (First name unknown)
  - Heyden, Helmuth von, 1932
  - Heydrich, Reinhard, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Himmler, Heinrich, 1936
  - Hindenburg, Paul von, 1933
  - Hitler, Adolf, 1933
  - Hitler Jugend Reichsjugendfuehrung, 1939
  - Hoevels, Paul, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Holtzmann, Otto, 1929
  - Illing, Oscar (editor of Die Neue Zeit, Chicago, U.S.A.), 1926, 1927
  - Jaeckel, 1933 (editor of the Kirchenblatt des Kirchenkreises Demmin) (First name unknown)
  - Der Jungdeutsche, 1924
  - Junkermann, 1933 (First name unknown) (Box 1)
  - Keunecke, F., 1943 (First name unknown)
  - Kiersten, 1930 (First name unknown)
  - Kingel, Max, 1926
  - Knauer, B., 1926
  - Koenenkamp, Helmuth, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Kogge, 1929 (First name unknown)
  - Koenig, S., 1929 (First name unknown)
  - Koenig, Marga, 1930
  - Krach, 1929 (First name unknown)
  - Kraeger, Professor, 1929 (First name unknown) (Box 1)
  - Krasigk, Schwerin von, 1935
  - Kuke, Wilhelm, 1933
  - Kummer, Georg, 1936
  - Kurth, Hans, 1929
  - Lassig, 1929 (first name unknown) (Box 1)
  - Last, 1932 (First name unknown)
  - Leder, Fritz, 1926
  - Lehmann, Otto, 1924, 1925
  - Lehwald, Hans-Rolf, 1925
  - Lemcke, Friedrich, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Liebel, Ludwig, 1926
  - Lippert, Dr. Julius, 1930
  - Loehde, 1935 (First name unknown)
  - Luck, von, 1926
  - Ludendorff, General Erich, 1923-1937 (Box 2)
  - Maier, Eugene, 1928
  - Maier, Theodore, 1936
  - Markel, O., 1926
  - Marx, Robert, 1931-1932
  - Mecklenburger, Warte, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Medem, Herold von (Graf), 1925, 1926
  - Miething, Hilde, 1938
  - Mosich, Dr., 1936 (First name unknown)
  - Mueffling, von, 1927 (First name unknown)
  - Muencheberg Der Buergeimeister als ortspolizeibehoerde, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Niederlausitz West, Tannenbergbund representative, 1933
  - Neuhaus, G., 1920, 1929 (First name unkown)
  - Neuruppin, Der Landrat in, 1933
  - Der Ostmaerker, 1933
  - Partay, Georg, 1925, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Pertz, F., 1936 (First name unknown)
  - Petzinger, Rudolf, 1932
  - Pfeifer, 1931, 1933 (First name unknown)
  - Der Politische Polizeikommandeur der Laender, 1936
  - Die Pommersche Zeitung, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Raab, Luise, 1932
  - Reichs und Preussiche Minister fuer Wissenschaft, Erziehnung und Volkbildung, 1936
  - Der Regierungspraesident, 1933
  - Reichsschrifttumskammer Gruppe Ruchhandel, 1937
  - Richter, Wilhelm, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Rippler, Heinrich, 1926
  - Rode, von, 1929 (First name unknown)
  - Roemisch, Bruno, 1926
  - Roter Adler, 1931
  - Roth, Dr. Armin, 1933, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Roeklin, 1932 (First name unknown)
  - Roethke, Heinrich, 1930, 1933
  - Ruegenwalder Zeithung, 1933
  - Rust, Wilhelm, 1936
  - Schellendorff, Bonsart von, 1928-1932 (Box 2)
  - Schmidt, Rudolf, 1936
  - Schneider, Edmund, 1935, 1936
  - Schneider, Robert, 1936
  - Schriewer, Dr., 1936
  - Schroeder, Paul, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Schulz, Authur, 1933
  - Schultz, Richard, 1930
  - Schumacher, 1929 (First name unknown)
  - Schwerin, Graf, 1929 (First name unknown)
  - Siekendorff, von (Freiherr), 1927, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Seelow, Landrat der, 1933
  - Das Schwarze Korps, 1936
  - Speromus, Carl, 1927
  - Der Stahlhelm, 1924-1925
  - Stephens, von, 1926 (First name unknown) (Box 2)
  - Stern, W. G., 1935 (First name unknown)
  - Stissel, 1936, (First name unknown)
  - Stolte, Georg, 1932
  - Stoessell, Harold, 1927
  - Stralsund in Pommern. Regierungspraesident, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Stettin Die Regierungspraesidenten, 1933
  - Thiede, Syndikus K., 1924, 1925
  - Thormaehlen, Herbert, 1930
  - Treu, Walter, 1932
  - Tschmaler, Herbert, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Tyron, Wilhelm, 1933
  - Unruh, Walter von, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Voelkisches Echo, 1924
  - Wedelstaedt, Wolff von, 1932
  - Wegerer, Alfred von, 1926 (Box 3)
  - Weiss, Carl, 1932
  - Wentzel, 1932 (First name unknown)
  - Wedemann, R., 1934 (First name unknown)
  - Wiest, 1936 (First name unknown)
  - Witte, Gerhard, 1932 (Box 3)
  - Wuerttemberg Politisches Landespolizeiamt, 1935
  - Wulle, R., 1924
  - Zehlendorfer Kirchenblatt, 1931
  - Ziegenruedberg, E., 1929
  - Ziegesar, Freiherr Ralf Berhard, 1926 (Box 3)
  - Zitzwitz, Max von, 1929, 1930
- Correspondence of Tannenbergbund Members, 1923-1939
  Letters of various members of the Tannenbergbund, a right-wing German political organization founded by General Erich Lundendorff. Collected by Robert Holtzmann and arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Ahlemann, Georg, 1928 (Box 3)
  - Alsleben, Kurt, 1933
  - Arminuis, 1926
  - Arnhould, Richard, 1928 (Box 3)
  - Bannke, A., 1926
  - Beck, 1936 (First name unknown)
  - Berlin Stadt/Bezirksamt Schoeneberg, 1927, 1936
  - Bonsell, 1927 (First name unknown)
  - Bovenschen, 1926 (First name unknown) (Box 3)
  - Braune, Hans, 1925
  - Breitenfeldt, J., 1936
  - Budenbender, 1929 (First name unknown)
  - Buehler, Anton, 1932, 1936
  - Burr, Hermann, 1933-1934 (Box 3)
  - Deutscher Kolonialverein Gesellschaft feur Nationale Siedlungs und Auslandspolitik, 1925
  - Diersch, Rose, 1925
  - Dinter, Artur, 1925
  - Dresdner Neueste Nachrichten, 1925
  - Engels, Willy, 1927 (Box 3)
  - Fintelmann, 1933 (First name unknown)
  - Das Freie Wort
  - Fritzsche, Georg, 1930-1933
  - Fuegner, Kurt, 1936
  - Funk, K., 1936 (First name unknown) (Box 3)
  - Geck, 1926 (First name unknown)
  - Hagemeher, Hans, 1935
  - Hall, 1933 (First name unknown)
  - Heimburg, von, 1935 (First name unknown)
  - Hellischer Voerkaempfer, 1925 (Box 3)
  - Hennig, Georg Otto, 1935
  - Hermann der Deutsche (pseudonym), 1930
  - Heyden, Helmuth von, 1933
  - Hoffmann, 1932
  - Jaeger, Wilhelm, 1925 (Box 3)
  - Jenaische Zeitung, 1924
  - Junkermann, 1933 (First name unknown)
  - Kurier fuer Niederbayern, 1926
  - Koch, Erich, 1930
  - Koerber, A.-V. von, 1925 (Box 3)
  - Lehmann, Otto, 1924, 1925
  - Lenk, Adolf, 1925-1927
  - Liebmann, 1936
  - Ludendorff, General Erich, 1925-1936 (Box 3)
  - Mack, Christian Wilhelm, 1927 (Box 3)
  - Martin, Benno, 1926
  - Marx, Robert, 1931-1932
  - Mischke, Ernst, 1932
  - Medem, Herold von (Graf), 1926
  - Moltke Graf von, 1933 (First name unknown) (Box 3)
  - Muelheim, L. Mueldner von, 1926
  - National Nothilse, 1929
  - Pommern Ost Tannenbergbund representative, 1932
  - Potsdam Reichsbanner Schwarz-Rot-Gold Bund, 1924
  - Prathmann, Wilhelm, 1936 (Box 3)
  - Prusshke, Max, 1932
  - Recke von Valmeistein, Friedrich Wilhelm von, n.d.
  - Roethke, Heinrich, 1930, 1933
  - Sack, Dr., 1926 (First name unknown)
  - Schedensack, Ernst Albrecht, 1936 (Box 3)
  - Schellendorff, Bonsart von, 1932-1933
  - Schemmel, 1926 (First name unknown)
  - Schiebuhr, Fritz, 1925
  - Schlageter, Albert Leo, 1925
  - Schmidt, Georg, 1924 (Box 3)
  - Schmold, Dr., 1933
  - Senftenberg, Der Buergermeister als Ortspolizei, 1933
  - Sonnenheim, Theodore Herrmann von, 1927
  - Thalacher - Schwarz Verlag, 1925
  - Tiemann, H., 1912, 1914 (First name unknown) (Box 3)
  - Unruh, Walter von, 1933
  - Wartmann, Rudolf, Jr., 1926
  - Weberstedt, Hans von, 1925-1927, 1932-1933
  - Weichart, Kurt, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Weicher, Theodore, 1936
  - Weidner, Edmund, 1927
  - Weikerstahal, Fischer von, 1935
  - Weiss, Carl, 1925, 1932
  - Weide, Dr., 1926
  - Winter, August, 1927 (Box 4)
  - Witte, Gerhard, 1932
  - Wulle, R., 1925
  - Ziegesar, Freiherr Bernhard, 1926
  - Ziegler, F., 1925 (Box 4)
- Subject File, 1923-1939 (Box 4-7)
  Addresses, letters, speeches, clippings, financial reports, notes, circulars, leaflets, newspapers, testimonials, pamphlets, memorabilia, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Anti-political/religious propaganda (Box 4)
  - Free Masons (Box 4)
  - Ludendorff, General Erich (Box 5)
  - Nationalsozialistiche Deutsche Arbeiter Partei (Box 5)
  - Tannenbergbund (Box 5-6)
  - "Folkish Movement" (Box 6-7)
- Miscellaneous, 1912-1941 (Box 7-8)
  Album of miscellaneous letters, clippings, leaflets, articles, money, maps.
  - Album of miscellaneous letters, clippings, leaflets, articles, money, and maps (Box 7-8)
- Microfilm
  - Negative microfilms of the correspondence series (boxes 1-3). (Reel 1-3)
- Photographs, undated
  - 11 photos including 2 photos of Adolf Hitler; 4 photos of Erich Ludendorff; 5 photos of members of the Tannenbergbund, undated (Box 49015 - 10.A-V, Folder A)
  - Print of Erich Ludendorff; a photo of Adolf Hitler and World War I German officers, undated (Folder mB)